Okay. Well, it's the era of Jefferson
and that means there's all kinds of
debates about the proper scope and role
of the federal government in the toddler
years of America. And I don't think it's
too much to say that these debates were
pretty dang juicy. So, if you're ready
to get them brain cows milked, let's get
to it. Okay, so Thomas Jefferson won the
election of 1800 and that was a pretty
big deal because it represented a
peaceful transfer of power between two
rival political parties. Now, remember
that the Federalist kind of dominated
the first years of the republic. You had
the boss president, George Washington,
and then you had his Kirkland's brand
knockoff, John Adams. And all the while,
the rival party, the Democratic
Republicans, led by Thomas Jefferson,
basically disagreed with dang near
everything the Federalists stood for and
the policies they enacted. But now it's
1800, y'all, and Thomas Jefferson is in
office. And just in case the
momentousness of what I just said is
lost on you, the peaceful transfer of
power between rival parties was not
really a thing in world history up to
that point. No, if a faction wanted to
strip their rivals of their power pants,
then usually someone was about to get
shot or stabbed or something. So, this
election was kind of a big deal in that
regard. But you didn't think that
peaceful transfer of power meant that
these two parties would stop fighting
about politics, did you? Don't be crazy.
No. The great weeping and nashing of
teeth between these two rival factions
would only heat up during the first part
of the 19th century. And the beef mainly
came down to the different way each side
interpreted the Constitution. But before
I tell you about that difference, as is
my custom, let me tell you about my A
Push Heimler review guide. It's got
everything you need to get an A in your
class and a five on your exam in May.
It's got exclusive whole unit review
videos that you're not going to find
here on YouTube, note guides to follow
along, practice questions, fulllength
practice exams, and answer keys for
every dang bit of them. So, if you need
help studying as fast as possible, then
check that link in the description.
Anyway, the rest of this video will only
make sense if you understand how these
rival parties interpreted the
Constitution. So, the Federalists were
loose constructionists, which means they
believe that the federal government
could rightly exercise powers that were
not explicitly stated in the
Constitution. For example, remember in
unit 3 when we talked about Hamilton's
National Bank? Nowhere in the
Constitution does it say that Congress
has the power to create a national bank.
But Hamilton, using a loose
constructionist framework, argued that
the necessary and proper clause in
Article One of the Constitution allowed
for a bank since other explicit powers
like tax collection and the regulation
of commerce made a bank, you know,
necessary and proper. Democratic
Republicans, on the other hand, were
strict constructionists, which means
they believe that the federal government
could only exercise power that was
explicitly granted by the Constitution.
In other words, if it ain't written,
they ain't fitting to do anything
without constitutional authority. So
again, from this perspective, the
Constitution says nothing about a
national bank and therefore the federal
government is forbidden from creating
it. Okay, now that you understand that
difference, let's talk about how
Jefferson brought his strict
constructionist Democratic Republican
principles to bear on the operation of
the federal government. And in case you
forgot, Democratic Republicans as a rule
loathed expansion of federal power. They
wanted to smack the federal piñata as
hard as they could until the power candy
fell out and scattered itself among the
states. That belief was built upon a
vision of the United States as primarily
an agrarian or farm-based nation. And at
the heart of that agrarian nation were
scores of yman farmers who owned their
own farms and engaged in small-scale
agriculture primarily with family labor.
So when you hear Jefferson's election
called the revolution of 1800, that's
what the revolution looked like in old
TJ's brain. An agrarian nation and a
limited government that served the needs
of the common citizen. And to be fair,
in some ways, Jefferson acted in line
with that conviction by repealing the
whiskey tax and reducing the debt of the
federal government by about half. But
here's where I tell you that under
Jefferson's leadership, he also did a
whole lot to expand the power of the
federal government. I'll give you two
examples. First was the Louisiana
purchase in 1803. For context, in 1799,
Napoleon Bonapart rose to power in
France. And one of his first moves was
to reclaim possession of their former
colony of Haiti after Tusant Luvatur and
his troops successfully revolted against
the French. But by 1803, the French were
defeated and Haiti remained in control
of its black le government. This event
seemed like a real good opportunity to
Jefferson to try to persuade the French
to open the port of New Orleans to US
merchant activity, which was especially
important to Western farmers. And so,
Jefferson sent James Monroe to France
with $2 million in his pocket to strike
a deal with Napoleon for the port.
However, with Haiti gone and more wars
to finance, Napoleon offered Monroe the
entire Louisiana territory for $15
million. Now, unfortunately, Monroe's
cell phone didn't get great service in
France, and so he couldn't call
Jefferson for advice. So, he went ahead
and accepted the deal. US territory
doubled. And you would think, hey, great
news, right? Well, when Monroe returned
and told Jefferson about the deal,
Jefferson just about pooped his pants.
Remember, this guy is a strict
constructionist. And nowhere in the
Constitution does it authorize a
president to purchase land from a
foreign government. But in the end,
Jefferson cleaned up his pants and
embraced the purchase since it afforded
millions of acres to settlers who would
then fulfill Jefferson's vision of an
agrarian America. But in so doing, there
is no doubt that the guy expanded
federal power. But there were definitely
vocal opponents to this purchase, and
their main beef was that it would be
exceedingly difficult to organize and
control such a vast territory. Not to
mention, it raised the contentious issue
about the spread of slavery into the new
states formed out of that territory. But
then Jefferson further expanded the
reach of the federal government by
commissioning the core of discovery to
explore and map the new territory. The
expedition was led by Merryweather Lewis
and William Clark and they spent 2 years
traveling and cataloging the features of
the Northwest Territory. And then
Zebulon Pike led similar expeditions to
explore the southern part of the
territory. And in doing so, the
information provided by these explorers
would expand federal power over the
territory. Since the data collected
would help inform future decisions about
statehood and potential conflicts with
Spanish and French settlers and the
displacement of American Indians whom
Jefferson hoped would assimilate to
American agrarian lifestyles to free up
further land for American settlement.
Okay. The second example of Jefferson's
expansion of federal power was the
Embargo Act of 1807, which was a federal
ban on international trade. Now, about 5
minutes after Jefferson cinched up his
presidential power pants, the Napoleonic
Wars erupted between Great Britain and
France. And each power sought an
alliance with the United States against
the other. And hey, this is Thomas
Jefferson, right? It's the guy who hated
Washington's refusal to support France
so much that he resigned his cabinet
position in protest. So, of course, old
Tommy is going to ally the US with
France, right? Yeah. No. For a whole
host of reasons, Jefferson decided to
uphold Washington's neutrality
proclamation and keep the US out of the
fight. But that snub got both Britain
and France more than a little saucy. And
so they retaliated by interrupting
American trade with their rival. So that
meant France and Britain seized US
merchant ships. They impounded the cargo
and forced merchants to fight on their
own ships. Like I could go on. And so
Jefferson went ahead and puffed up his
chest and led Congress to pass the
Embargo Act which essentially cut off
all US trade with Britain and France and
dang near everyone else in the world on
the belief that such an act would force
Britain and France to respect US
neutrality. So Jefferson was like, "How
y'all like me now?" To which Great
Britain and France responded, "Huh,
how's your economy going, bro?" To which
Jefferson responded, "Ah, crap."
>> So, while Jefferson's aim was to force
these countries to recognize US
neutrality, the complete blockage of
foreign trade created significant
hardship for Americans of many different
strikes. Turns out a lot of Americans
depended not only on selling goods to an
international market, but also buying
goods on an international market. And
Jefferson went ahead and led Congress to
drop a huge legislative dump on
Americans economic well-being. And so as
an economic recession continued a debate
about the proper scope of federal power
started gathering steam. In this
particular case, the federal government
didn't just attempt to regulate
international trade, it shut down trade
almost wholesale and cause serious
economic trouble. And remember,
according to Jefferson's own principles,
federal power bad. And here he was
wielding enormous amounts of federal
power to cut off trade with France and
Britain. Not to mention using federal
power to crack down on smugglers who
were flouting the law. And worst of all,
it was the United States that suffered
most on account of this policy. Okay.
Now, the final expansion of federal
power you need to know during this time
is the strengthening of the Supreme
Court. And all of this happened under
the leadership of a Federalist Chief
Justice by the name of John Marshall,
whose actions to beef up the power of
the Supreme Court led to bitter debates
between the two parties.
>> Now, recall that the Constitution gave
relatively little authoritative
instruction on the role and power of the
Supreme Court. But by means of several
important decisions, the Supreme Court
gained power during this period and
claimed a co-equal place with the other
two branches of government. And I'll
mention two of those cases. First was
Marberry v. Madison in 1803. And here's
the quick background. So one of John
Adams's final acts as president was to
stuff the federal courts with federalist
judges, an act that became known as
Adams's midnight appointments. And since
federal judges served for a life, the
Jefferson administration interpreted the
appointments as a way for federalists to
frustrate the future plans and policies
of the Democratic Republicans.
Therefore, Jefferson's Secretary of
State James Madison solved this problem
by not delivering the commissions to
several judges. So, in response, some of
those judges sued Madison to get their
commissions in the case came before the
Supreme Court. And in his written
decision, John Marshall did something
exceedingly momentous. First, he said
that the court had no power to compel
Madison to deliver the commissions.
Okay, that's not a huge deal. But
second, Marshall asserted that it was
the Supreme Court's role to be the final
interpreter of the Constitution, a power
known as judicial review. Why are you
not falling out of your seat right now?
This was massive. Like in claiming the
power of judicial review, Marshall
elevated the power of the Supreme Court
to equality with the other two branches.
And that further confirmed the
constitutional foundations of the
separation of powers and checks and
balances. And yet even further,
Marshall's claim of judicial review
overturned Jefferson's argument in the
Virginia and Kentucky resolutions that
we talked about in unit 3. In other
words, the court has the final say on
what was or was not constitutional and
not the states. Like this was a huge
deal. Okay. Now, the second case that
illustrates a growth of federal power
under Marshall is McCullik v. Maryland
in 1819. The big idea here is that this
case helped establish the supremacy of
federal law over state law. Now, by this
time, Congress had chartered a second
national bank over the loud objections
of the Democratic Republicans who argued
that a national bank represented too
much federal power over the state.
Therefore, in order to keep that power
in check, legislators in Maryland passed
a tax on the bank, which represented an
effort to maintain state power above
federal power. But when this case came
before the Supreme Court, John Marshall
wrote in his decision that the bank was
constitutional on grounds of a loose
constructionist interpretation of the
necessary and proper clause. And
ultimately, this decision along with
others under Marshall's leadership
established the supremacy of federal law
above state law, thus expanding federal
power. Okay, you can click here to watch
my other videos from unit 4, or you can
click here to grab my A Push Himler
review guide, which has everything you
need to study as fast as possible. And
I'm glad you came around, and I'll catch
you on the flip-flop. I'm Laurat.